本节我跟大家讨论另一种形式的加密
In this segment, I want to tell you about
another form of encryption, called format
叫做保格式加密。这个加密也是经常在实际中遇到
preserving encryption. This is again
something that comes up in practice quite
特别是加密信用卡号
often, especially when it comes to
encrypting credit card numbers. And, so,
我们看它是如何工作的。记得一般来说
信用卡号有16位数字
let's see how it works. Remember that a
typical credit card number is sixteen
分成4组，每组4个数字
digits, broken into four blocks of four
digits each. You've probably heard before
大家很可能听过，前6个数字叫做BIN码
that the first six digits are what's
called the BIN number, which represent the
代表了发行方的ID。例如，所有的VISA信用卡
issuer ID. For example, all credit cards
issued by VISA always start with the digit
都以数字4开头；所有的MasterCard信用卡
都以数字51或55开头，等等。。
four; all credit cards issued by
MasterCard start with digits 51 to 55, and
后面9位数字是帐号
so on and so forth. The next nine digits
are actually the account number that is
是每个消费者特有的，而最后一位数字是一个校验和
specific to the, to the particular
customer and the last digit is a check sum
是由前15位数字计算得到的。有大约20000个BIN码
that's computed from the previous fifteen
digits. So there are about 20,000 BIN
所以如果你算一下，实际上大约有2的42次方个
numbers and so if you do the calculation
it turns out there are about 2 to the 42
可能的信用卡号，对应于42位信息
possible credit card numbers which
corresponds to about 42 bits of
你需要编码这42位信息，如果你想紧密地表示信用卡号
information that you need to encode if you
want to represent a credit card number
问题是，假设我们想加密信用卡号
compactly. Now the problem is this.
Suppose we wanted to encrypt credit card
使得当用户在销售终端刷信用卡时
numbers, so that when the user swipes the
credit card number at the point of sale
比如在商家的现金登记处
terminal, namely at the, you know,
the merchant's cash register. The cash
现金登记处是一种销售终端
register, this is called a point of sale
terminal, goes ahead and encrypts the
使用密钥k加密信用卡号，并始终保持加密
credit card number using a key k and
it's encrypted all the way until it goes
直到银行需要，或甚至是VISA要用
to the acquiring bank or maybe even beyond
that, maybe even all the way when it goes
现在，问题是这些信用卡号经历了
to VISA. Now, the problem is that these
credit card numbers actually pass through
许多处理环节。它们都希望获得某些
many, many, many processing points. All of
them expect to get basically something
看起来像是信用卡号的信息
that looks like a credit card number as a
result. So if we simply wanted to encrypt
如果我们只想在端点加密，在另一端点解密
something at the end point, at one end
point, and decrypt it at the other end
这并不容易，因为如果我们使用AES加密
point, it's actually not that easy because
if all we did was encrypt it using AES,
即使我们使用的是确定的AES，加密后的信用卡号
even if we just used deterministic AES,
the output of the encrypted credit card
将是128位的分组，16字节，将会从一个系统发送给
number would be 128 bit block. Sixteen
bytes that would be, that would need to be
下一个系统，直到它到达目的地。但是这些处理节点
sent from one system to the next, until it
reaches its destination. But each one of
每个都必须改变，因为它们都希望获得信用卡号
these processors, then, would have to be
changed, because they're all expecting to
所以问题是，我们能否在现金登记处加密
get credit card numbers. And so the
question is, can we encrypt at the cash
使得获得的加密本身看上去像是一个信用卡号
register, such that the resulting
encryption itself looks like a credit card
因此，这些中间系统都无需做出改变
number. And as a result, none of these
intermediate systems would have to be
只有端点需要改变。通过这样做
changed. Only the endpoints would have to
be changed. And in doing so we would
我们实际上获得了端到端的加密，
不需要改变太多的沿途的软件
actually obtain end-to-end encryption
without actually having to change a lot of
那么问题是，我们如何构造这种机制
software along the way. So the question
then is, again, can we have this mechanism
即所谓的保格式加密，加密一个信用卡号
called format preserving encryption, where
encrypting a credit card itself produces
能产生某些类似信用卡号的信息呢？这是我们的目标
something that looks like a credit card?
So that's our goal. The encrypted credit
加密的信用卡号应该看起来像一个正常的有效信用卡号
card number should look like a regular
valid credit card number. So this is the
这是保格式加密的目标。更为抽象地，我们试图
goal of format preserving encryption. More
abstractly what it is we're trying to do,
在集合｛0,1,...,S-1｝上构建一个伪随机置换
is basically build a pseudo random
permutation on the set zero to S minus one
S是任意的。那么对于信用卡号的集合来说，S大约为
for any given S. So for the set of credit
card numbers, S would be roughly, you
2的42次方。事实上，它并不是严格的2的42次方
know, two to the 42. In fact, it's gonna
be, not exactly two to the 42. It's gonna
它是某个有趣的接近2的42次方的数。我们的目标是
be some funny numbers that's around two to
the 42. And our goal is to build a PRP
构建一个从0到S-1的区间上的PRP
that acts exactly on the interval, zero to
S minus one. And what we're given as input
我们已有某个PRF，比如像AES，这个PRF可以
处理长得多的分组，比如说
is some PRF, say, something like AES, that
acts on much larger blocks, say, acts on
像AES的16字节分组。那么某种意义上，
我们试图压缩这个PRF的定义域
sixteen byte blocks. So we're trying to,
in some sense, shrink the domain of the
使之适应我们已有的数据。问题是怎么办？
PRF to make it fit the data that we're
given. And the question is basically how
我们一旦有了这么一个机制
to do that. Well, once we have such a
construction we can easily use it to
就可以使用它轻松加密信用卡号了。
我们取给定的信用卡号
encrypt credit card numbers. What we would
do is we would take the, a given credit
我们加密它，使得它能用
card number. We would encode it such that
now it's represented as a number between
从0到信用卡号总数之间的某个数来表示。
那么我们应用我们的PRP，这样一来
zero and the total number of credit card
numbers. Then we would apply our PRP so we
我们就加密这个信用卡号
would encrypt this credit card number, you
know, using construction number two from
使用确定性加密一节里的2号机制。然后
我们把最后的数映射到一个正常的值
the deterministic encryption segment. And
then we would map the final number back to
一个有效的信用卡号
be a regular, to look like val--, regular,
valid credit card number and then send
然后发送。那么这也是非扩展加密
this along the way. So this is, this
is again non expanding encryption. The
如前所述，我们目前最多只能使用PRP加密
best we can do, as we said before is to
encrypt using a PRP except again the
不过这里困难之处在于，我们需要一个PRP
在这个看上去很有趣的集合上操作
technical challenge is we need a PRP that
acts on this particular funny looking set
从0到S-1，S是预先指定的。那么我的目标是
from zero to S-1 for this prespecified
value of S. So my goal is to show you how
告诉大家如何组建这个机制，一旦我们知道了
如何加密，大家就会知道
to construct this and once we see how to
do it, you will also know how to encrypt
如何加密信用卡号，使得密文本身也是信用卡号
credit card number so that the resulting
cipher text is itself a credit card
那么这个机制共两步。首先我们压缩PRF的定义域
number. So the construction works in two
steps. The first thing we do is we shrink
｛0,1｝^n，比如说AES的｛0,1｝^128
our PRF from the set ｛0,1｝ to the n, say
｛0,1｝ to the 128 in the case of AES,
压缩到｛0,1｝^t，t是最接近以2为底，S的对数的值
to ｛0,1｝ to the t where t is the
closest power of two to the value S.
(换句话说，2的t次方最接近S)
比如说S是某个很大的数，接近2的41次方，那么t就是42
So say S is some crazy number around two to
the 41. T would basically be then 42
因为那最接近以2为底，S的对数，且大于S
because that's the closest power of two
that's just above the value S. So the
那么这个机制使用Luby-Rackoff机制
construction is basically gonna use the
Luby-Rackoff construction. What we need
我们需要一个PRF F'，在长度为t/2的分组上操作
is a PRF F prime that acts on blocks of
size t over two. So imagine for example
例如，在信用卡号的例子中，t将是42，
因为我们说过，2的42次方最接近S
in the credit card case, t would be 42
because two to the 42 we said is the
也比S大。S是所有信用卡号的总数
closest power of two that's bigger than,
than, than S. S is the number of credit,
那么我们需要一个PRF，在21位输入上操作
total number of credit cards. Then we would
need a PRF now that acts on 21-bit
一种方法是取AES分组密码，把它当成
inputs. So one way to do that is simply to
take the AES block cipher, treat it as a
128位输入的PRF，然后截断输出
PRF on 128-bit inputs, and then simply
truncate the output to the least
取低21位。我们得到21位的值
significant 21 bits. Okay, so we were
given a 21 bit value. We would append
我们在它后面附0，以获得128位。
然后我们对它应用AES
zeros to it so that we get 128 bits as a
result. We would apply AES to that and
然后将结果截断成21位。现在我应该告诉大家
then we would truncate back to 21 bits.
Now I should tell you that that's actually
这是一个简单的方式，但它不是最好的
a simple way to do it but it's actually
not the best way to do it. There are
实际上有更好的截断n位PRF的方法，以生成t位PRF
actually better ways to truncate a PRF on
n bits to a PRF on t over two bits.
但对于本节的目标，我刚刚说的截断方法已经足够好了
But for our pur--, for the purposes of this
segment, the truncation method I just said
我们姑且先使用它。好，那么现在
is good enough. So let's just use that
particular method. Okay, so now, we've
我们已经把我们的AES分组密码转换成了
一个t/2位的PRF，比如说，21位
converted our AES block cipher into a PRF
on t over two bits, say, on 21 bits. But
但我们真正想要的是一个PRP。所以我们只要
把我们的新PRF F'
what we really want is a PRP. And so what
we'll do is we'll plug our new PRF, F prime,
直接带入到Luby-Rackoff机制中。如果大家还记得
directly into the Luby-Rackoff
construction. If you remember, this is
这是一个Feistel机制。我们讨论DES时，见过它
basically a Feistel construction. We saw
this when we talked about DES. It's a,
Luby-Rackoff使用了3轮Feistel网络，
我们知道这将一个安全的PRF
Luby-Rackoff used three rounds, and we
know that this converts a secure PRF into
转换成一个安全的PRP。换句话说，我们从一个安全的
a secure PRP on twice the block size. In
other words, we started from a secure PRF
21位PRF出发，这样做Luby-Rackoff会给我们一个安全的42位PRF
on 21 bits, and that will give us, and
Luby-Rackoff will give us a secure PRF on
(事实上，也是安全的42位PRP)
这正是我们想要的。现在，我应该告诉大家
42 bits, which is what we wanted. Now, I
should tell you that the error parameters
Luby-Rackoff机制中的误差参数并不是最好的
in the Luby-Rackoff construction are not as
good as they could be. And, in fact, a
事实上，迭代7轮Feistel网络会更好。换句话说
better thing to do is to use seven rounds
of Feistel. So in other words, we'll do
我们迭代7次，每次使用不同的密钥。大家注意
this seven times; every time we'll use a
different key. So you notice, here, we're
我们只使用这三个密钥。我们应该这样做7遍
only using three keys. We should be using,
we should be doing this seven times using
使用7个不同的密钥。然后这有一个很好的结果
seven different keys. And then there's a
nice result, due to Patarin, that
Patarin证明了这个7轮机制具有最好的误差参数
shows that the seven-round construction
basically has as good an error
那么这个安全性定理里的误差参数
terms as possible. So the error terms in
the security theorem will basically be two
将是2的t次方，所以我们现在就有了一个伪随机置换
to the T. Okay. So now we have a pseudo
random permutation that operates on close
在约2的S次方个值上操作。但这还是不够好
power of two to the value of S. But that's
not good enough. We actually want to get a
我们想要一个在集合｛0,1,...,S-1｝上的伪随机置换
pseudo random permutation on the set zero
to S minus one. So step two will take us
那么第二步，取｛0,1｝^t里的值，映射到
我们感兴趣的集合｛0,1,...,S-1｝
down from ｛0,1｝ to the T, to the actual
set zero to the S minus one that we're
这个机制也很犀利
interested in. And this construction is,
again, really, really acute, so let me show
我告诉大家它是如何工作的。我们有这个PRP了，
可以置换这个t位集合里的元素
you how it works. So, again, we're given
this PRP that operates on a power of two.
我们想让这个PRP可以在更小的集合上工作
And we wanna go down to a PRP that
operates on something slightly smaller.
好，那么这是这个机制的工作过程。
我们有输入X，X属于我们想要的集合｛0,1,...,S-1｝
Okay, so here's on the construction works.
Basically we're given input X in the set
我们接下来
zero to S minus one that we want. And what
we're going to do is we're going to
一次次地迭代以下流程：首先
iterate the following procedure again
and again. So first of all we map X into
我们把X映射到某个临时变量Y。现在我们加密输入X
this temporary variable Y. And now we're
just gonna encrypt the input X and put the
把结果放在Y里。如果Y在我们的目标集合里，
我们就停止迭代，然后输出Y
result into Y. If Y is inside of our
target set, we stop and we output Y. If
如果不在，我们就继续迭代下去，直到
not we iterate this again and again and
again and again and again until finally Y
Y落在了我们的目标集合里，然后我们输出这个Y值
falls into our target set and then we
output that value. So in a picture, let me
我以图像的形式解释一下。我们从目标集合中的一点出发
explain how this works. So we start from a
point in our target set. And now, now we
现在我们应用函数E，我们可能会把这个点映射到
我们的目标集合的外面
apply the, the function E and we might be
mapped into this point outside our target
那么我们就不会停止，我们反复应用函数E
set, so we're not gonna stop. So now we
apply the function E again and we might
我们可能映射到这个点，现在我们再次应用函数E
be mapped into this point and now we apply
the function E again and now all of a
突然间我们映射到了这个点，然后我们停止迭代，
这就是我们的输出
sudden we map into this point, and then we
stop, and that's our output. Okay, so
这就是我们如何映射集合｛0,1,..,S-1｝中的点
that's how we map points between from zero
to S minus one, to other points in the
到这个集合本身的。很显然，这是可逆的
zero to S minus one. It should be pretty
clear that this is invertible. To invert,
求逆时，我只要解密，然后反方向逐次尝试
all I'll do is I'll just decrypt and walk,
kind of, in the opposite direction. So
解密，再解密。。直到落在集合｛0,1,..,S-1｝中
I'll decrypt, and then decrypt, and then
decrypt, until finally, I fall into the
这就给我一个点的逆置换结果，正是我想要的
set, zero to S minus one. And that gives
me the inverse of the point that I wanted
事实上这是一个PRP。问题是，它是否是一个安全的PRP？
to. So this is, in fact, a PRP. The
question is whether it's a secure PRP, and
我们待会就会看到。不过在这之前，我问大家
we'll see that in just a minute. But before
that, let me ask you, how many iterations
你觉得我们需要循环多少次呢？
在问这个问题之前，我想再提醒大家
do you expect that we're gonna need? And
I wanna remind you again, before I ask you
事实上，S小于2的t次方，但大于2的t-1次方
that question, that, in fact, S is less than
two to the T, but is more than two to the T-1.
特别地，S大于2的t次方的一半
So in particular S is greater than two to
the T over two. And my question to you
我给大家的问题是，我们平均需要多少次迭代，
知道该过程收敛？
now is how many iterations are we gonna
need, on average, until this process converges?
那么答案是我们平均需要迭代两次
So the answer is we're going to need two iterations,
(提示：几何分布的期望)
这是一个很小的迭代次数
so really just a small
constant number of iterations. And so this
这给我们一个非常有效的机制
will give us a very, very efficient
mechanism that will move us down from
让我们从｛0,1｝^t转变到｛0,1,..,S-1｝。
那么现在我们来讨论其安全性
｛0,1｝ to the T to zero to the S-1. So now
when we talk about security, it turns out
实际上这一步是紧的，换句话说，没有附加的
this step here is tight. In other words,
there is really no additional security
安全性开销，从｛0,1｝^t到｛0,1,..,S-1｝
cost to going down from two to the T to
zero to S-1. And the reason that's true,
其原因是有个很犀利的定理可以证明。但我这里不给出证明
it's actually again a very acute theorem
to prove, but I, I won't do it here. Maybe
也许留给大家作为练习。这是在说，如果你给我
I'll leave it as an exercise for you guys
to argue. Which says that if you give me
(提示：从概率出发，会涉及一个等比数列求和的极限)
两个集合Y和X，Y包含于X，那么应用刚才我们看到的变换
any two sets Y and X, where Y is contained
inside of X, then applying the
我们从一个X到X的随机置换出发
transformation that we just saw to a
random permutation from X to X actually
得到一个Y到Y的随机置换。这意味着
如果我们从一个X上的真随机置换出发
gives a random permutation from Y to Y. So
this means that if we started with a truly
最后会得到一个Y上的真随机置换
random permutation on X, you'll end up
with a truly random permutation on Y. And
因此，我们开始时的置换与X上的随机置换不可区分
since, well, the permutation we're
starting with is indistinguishable from
我们最后得到的置换也和Y上的随机置换不可区分
random on X, we'll end up with a
permutation that's indistinguishable from
好，这个机制是紧致的，如我所说
random on Y. Okay, so this is a very tight
construction and as I said, the first step
第一步的分析与Luby-Rackoff的分析一致
actually is basically, the analysis is the
same as the Luby-Rackoff analysis. In
事实上，我说过，根据Patarin的分析，最好是用7轮
fact, it's better to use as I said, the
Patarin analysis using seven rounds. So
那么这里，有一点安全性的开销
actually here, there's a bit of cost in
security. But, overall, we get a
总的来说，我们获得一个安全PRP的机制
construction that is a secure PRP for
actually, not such good security
虽然安全参数不是很好，但这是我们能够组建的好的安全PRP
parameters, but nevertheless, this is a
good secure PRP that we can construct that
可以在｛0,1,..,S-1｝上操作
actually will operate on the range zero to
S minus one. This in turn will allow us to
这就允许我们去加密信用卡号，使得密文
看起来也像是信用卡号了
encrypt credit card numbers such that the
cipher text looks like a credit card
我想再强调一下，这里没有任何的完整性
number. And again, I want to emphasize
that there's no integrity here. The best
我们能取得的最好的结果是确定的CPA安全
we can achieve here is just
deterministic CPA security. No cipher text
没有任何密文完整性，没有任何随机性。好。本章完结
integrity, and no randomness at all. Okay.
So this concludes this module. And as
通常我们会指出一些阅读材料
usual I want to point to a few reading
materials that you can take a look at if
如果你对本章的某些话题感兴趣，可以读一读
you're interested in learning more about
anything that we discussed in this module.
首先，我们讨论密钥推导时
So first of all, the HKDF construction
that we talked about for key derivation is
HKDF机制在2010年Hugo Krawczyk的文章里有所描述
described in a paper from 2010 by Hugo
Krawczyk. Deterministic encryption, The
确定性加密，SIV模式在这篇论文里有所讨论
SIV mode that we described is discussed in
this paper over here. The EME mode that we
我们描述了EME模式，可以让我们构建一个
宽分组的伪随机置换
described that allows us to build a, a
wider block pseudo random permutation is
EME模式在这篇Halevi和Rogaway的论文里描述
described in this paper here by Halevi and
Rogaway. Tweakable block ciphers that
微调分组密码，引入了用于硬盘加密的XTS模式
actually led to the XTS mode of operation
that's used for disk encryption is
在这篇论文里描述。最后，保格式加密
described in this paper here. And finally,
a format preserving encryption is described
在这最后一篇论文里描述。本章完结
in this last paper that I point to over
here. Okay so this concludes this module.
下一章我们开始看如何交换密钥
And in the next module we gonna start
looking at how to do key exchange.